Exercise 5-2. Double vowel with R. Refer to the subsequent lists of sounds and
words as you work through each of the directions that follow them. Repeat each
sound, first the vowel, and then the R, and each word in columns 1 to 3. We'll
read all the way across. A-er, ha-erd, hard, e-er, he-er, hear, e-er, she-er,
share, o-er, mo-er, more, er-er, were, ur, were. We'll next read column three only.
Try to keep that doubled sound, but let the vowel flow smoothly into the ur.
Imagine a double stair step that cannot be avoided. Don't make them two staccato
sounds though, like ha-urred. Instead, flow them smoothly over the double stair
step. Ready? Hard, hear,
share, more, were. Of course they're not that long. This is an exaggeration and
you're going to shorten them up once you get better at that sound. When you say the
first one, hard, to get your jaw open for the ha, imagine that you're getting ready
to bite into an apple, ha. Then for the er sound, you'd bite into it, hard, hard.
Practice five times on your own. At this point, the American R can be a little difficult
to figure out. With words like where and were, it's confusing to know which one has
two different vowel sounds, where, and which one just has the er, were. When
there's a full vowel, you must make sure to give it its complete sound and not chop
it short, where. For words with only the schwa plus R, er, don't try to introduce
another vowel sound before the R regardless of spelling. The following
words, for example, don't have any other vowel sounds in them. Word, hurt, girl,
pearl. The following exercise will further clarify this for you.